Guide to the Confederate States of America Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Confederate States of America collection
1861-1865
GEN MSS 463
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.3
(3 boxes)
Correspondence and official documents originating from various CSA government departments and from individual Confederate states, 1861-65. Includes correspondence of Jefferson Davis, Confederate cabinet members and congressmen, and other officials, as well as official reports of Civil War battles and events, estimates of expenditures and appropriations, petitions, special orders, forms, passes, receipts, bonds, tax records, and other documents. While the bulk of the material is administrative in nature, many of the documents, such as tax records and discharge papers, concern particular individuals, and there are a few letters from private citizens, such as one to President Davis from two women who offer to go behind enemy lines. The collection also includes designs for an alternate Confederate flag.
Confederate States of America
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection of papers acquired by gift and purchase from various sources, indicated on individual folders where known. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence and official documents originating from various CSA government departments and from individual Confederate states, 1861-1865. The bulk of the material is bureaucratic in nature (e.g. reports and official correspondence), but there are a few letters from private citizens, and many of the documents, such as army discharge papers and medical certificates, concern particular individuals. Information about specific Civil War battles and events can be found throughout the collection in letters and reports. The papers are organized into three series: Correspondence, Documents, and Other Material.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: Correspondence of Jefferson Davis and Other Correspondence. The first consists of letters to President Davis, from members of his Cabinet and from citizens, and four brief letters of transmittal from Davis to the CSA Congress. Letters from Cabinet members include two detailed reports from Stephen R. Mallory, Secretary of the Navy: one concerns a naval engagment at Hampton Roads, Virginia, in 1862; the other concerns the seizure of the CSS Florida in the neutral port of Bahia, Brazil, by the USS Wachusett on October 7, 1864. One of the three letters from citizens is from two women in Georgia who offer to undertake dangerous missions behind enemy lines for the Confederate cause.
The second subseries, Other Correspondence, consists chiefly of correspondence between cabinet members and congressmen concerning government business, but also contains letters from Army generals and other officers reporting on military actions, including the battle of Malvern Hill. Also included are letters from the Spanish and French Consuls, and a letter from Indian Agent Douglas Cooper concerning the Confederacy's relations with the Choctaw and Chickasaw nations.
Series II, Documents, consists of reports, estimates of expenditures and appropriations, petitions, forms, passes, receipts, certificates, orders, bonds, tax records, and other official documents issued or collected by the CSA and by individual Confederate state governments. It is organized into nine subseries: Army, Congress, Department of State, Medical Purveyor's Office, Navy, Treasury Department, War Department, Individual State Governments, and Other Documents.
Army documents concerning specific regiments or divisions include field returns from the Second Georgia Battalion and General R. H. Anderson's Division; Casualty and Capture reports from General William Mahone's Division (formerly Anderson's Division); a report on the actions of General Rode's Brigade at Seven Pines; and a guard report of the Thirty-Third North Carolina Regiment. Other Army papers include a "List of Ordnance left on Morris Island on the night of its evacuation," a "Ladies' address to the Soldiers of Longstreet's Corps.," and documents concerning prisoners of war and military hospitals.
Other CSA government documents include petitions to the Secretary of the Treasury and the Senate to raise the salaries of government employees due to rapid inflation of Confederate currency; special orders suspending Habeas Corpus in Salisbury, North Carolina and Atlanta, Georgia; documents from Mississippi and South Carolina concerning the use of slaves in the CSA Army; resolutions passed in Pocahonta County, Virginia, concerning the inadequacy of defenses provided by the Confederacy against invasion; and several proposed designs for an alternate Confederate flag.
Other Documents contains a statement or appeal by former United States Acting Secretary of War William R. Drinkard regarding his neglected application for the post of Chief of the Bureau of War in the Confederate Government, and a pass issued by the United States Army in 1867, granting a North Carolina citizen permission to carry a gun.
Series III, Other Material, contains paper and envelopes said to have been taken from the Confederate Congress Hall during the seizure of Richmond, and two canvas letter or money bags.
Chickasaw Indians -- Government relations; Choctaw Indians -- Government relations; Flags -- Confederate States of America; Women spies -- Confederate States of America; Confederate States of America -- Foreign relations; Confederate States of America -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Confederate States of America -- Politics and government; Confederate States of America; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Local government records; Military records; Passports; Receipts (financial records); State government records; Tax records; Allan, Thompson; Benjamin, J. P. (Judah Philip), 1811-1884; Benning, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1814-1875; Bragg, Thomas, 1810-1872; Cooper, Douglas Hancock, 1815-1879; Cowdin, V. G., Mrs. (Virginia Georgia), 1818-1882; Cruger, Lewis; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889; Drinkard, Wm. R. (William R.); Elmore, E. C.; Harrison, Burton Norvell, 1838-1904; Hunter, R. M. T. (Robert Mercer Taliaferro), 1809-1887; Longstreet, James, 1821-1904; Mahone, William, 1826-1895; Mallory, Stephen R. (Stephen Russell), 1813-1873; Memminger, C. G. (Christopher Gustavus), 1803-1888; Morris, Charles Manigault; Randolph, George Wythe, 1818-1867; Reagan, John H. (John Henninger), 1818-1905; Roane, A.; Rodes, Robert Emmett, 1829-1864; Seddon, James A. (James Alexander), 1815-1880; Williams, John S. (John Stuart), 1818-1898; Florida (Cruiser); Wachusett (Steamer)
- Correspondence, 1861-1865; Series I; 0.21; (36 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is organized into two subseries: Jefferson Davis and Other Correspondence. Each is arranged alphabetically by sender.
  - JEFFERSON DAVIS
    - Incoming
      - Cowdin, Virginia G., Liberty, Miss., regarding her book Ellen, or, The Fanatic's Daughter, 1861 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Mallory, S. R., Secretary of the Navy, 1862 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        "Official report of the Naval Engagement between the James River Squadron [...] and the enemy's fleet in Hampton Roads"
      - Mallory, S. R., 1865 Feb 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Accompanies a copy of the report of Lieutenant Commander Charles Manigault Morris on the seizure of the CSS Florida by the USS Wachusett in the port of Bahia, Brazil on October 7, 1864; the report consists of copies of letters written by Morris, the ship's Paymaster Richard Taylor, CSA agent James Dwyer, L. de Videcky, and Antonio Joachim da Silva Gomes, President of the Province of Bahia
      - Memminger, C. G., Secretary of the Treasury, 1862 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Randolph, George W., Secretary of War, 1862 Oct 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        "In relation to the seizure, by military officers along several railroad lines, of produce and provisions, and prohibiting their transportation"
      - Trotter, Mrs. M. E., and Miss E. P. [Burel?], Danville, Georgia, 1865 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Offering to bear dispatches behind enemy lines
      - Roberts, D. B., Parish of St. Helena, Louisiana, 1861 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Proposing a day of fasting
    - Outgoing
      - To Congress, 1862 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - To Congress, 1862 Mar 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - To Congress, accompanied by a letter from Secretary of War James A. Seddon, 1863 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - To Congress, accompanied by a letter from Secretary of War James A. Seddon, 1864 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - OTHER CORRESPONDENCE
    - Allan, Thompson, Commissioner of Taxes, to P. N. Gilson, 1864 Jul 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Baker, G. A., CSA Depository, Lexington, Va., to E. C. Elmore, Treasurer, 1864 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Benning, Henry L., 17 Reg Ga. Vols., near Darleytown road, to "Gen", 1862 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      "Report of what the 17th Regiment did at Garnett's House 27 June 1862"
    - Bragg, Thomas, Attorney General, to C. G. Memminger, 1862 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bruen, C. T., to M. M. Lipscomb, 1864 Jan 14 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cooper, Douglas H., to Elias Rector, Superintendent of Indian Affairs, 1862 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Regarding the Choctaw and Chickasaw Nations
    - Cooper, G. P., to James M. Baker, 1863 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Cruger, Lewis, Comptroller, Treasury Department, to C. G. Memminger, 1864 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Dayan, E. S. to Richard Walker, Senator of Alabama, 1864 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Elliott, Stephen D., to John Elliott, 1863 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Written on the verso of a printed notice to voters of the Eleventh Congressional District, Virginia, from John Lechter
    - Faust, L. Augusta, of New Hope, S.C., to Vice President Alexander Stephens, 1862 Mar 21
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: box 2, folder 58
    - [Forio?], H., Colonel, 5th Louisiana Regiment, to General S. Cooper, 1862 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Harrison, Burton N. to the President of the Senate, 1865 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Henderson, F. M., telegram to W. Smith, 1865 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hunter, R. M. T., Secretary of State, to C. G. Memminger, 1862 Feb 13
      See: box 2, folder 62
    - [Lawas?] to C. T. Bruen, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Longstreet, J., to General Magruder, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Mahone, William, to [J. J.?] Anderson, General Huger's Division, 1862 Jul 15 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Report on the conduct and casualties of the 2nd Brigade of Georgia Volunteers in the Battle of Malvern Hill
    - Memminger, C. G., to R. W. Barnwell, Chairman, Committee on Finance, 1863 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Regarding petition for higher salaries by clerks in the Treasury Department
      See also: box 2, folder 68
    - Moncada, Munoz de, Spanish Consul, to Brig. General Thomas Jordan, 1863 Feb 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      "Submitted to the Hon. Sec. of War for the information of Congress, Febr of 64"
    - Navy Department, to Herschel V. Johnson, 1865 Feb 13 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Palfrey, Ed. A., War Department, to Lucius J. Gartrell, House of Representatives, 1864 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Paul, Alfred, French Consul, to J. P. Benjamin, Secretary of State, 1865 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Randolph, George W., to Brig. General H. T. Hays, 1862 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Raoul, N. G., to T. J. [Semms?], 1864 Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Reagan, John H., Postmaster General, to C. G. Memminger, 1864 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Roane, A., to C. G. Memminger, 1864 Feb 8
      See: box 2, folder 66
    - Williams, John S., Brigadier General, to Major General Samuel Jones, 1864 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Regarding operations of troops under his command in East Tennesee, 1863 Jun 27-Oct 15; accompanied by forwarding ALS from Jones to General Samuel Cooper; inscribed "Official Copy: Res. submitted to the Hon. Sec. of War for the information of Congress, Feb 3/64"
- Documents, 1861-1867; Series II; 0.4; (54 folders)
  This series is organized into nine subseries: Army, Congress, Department of State, Medical Purveyor's Office, Navy, Treasury Department, War Department, Individual State Governments, and Other Documents. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by issuing department or, if that is not known, by title.
  - ARMY
    - 2nd Georgia Battalion, "Efficient and Non Efficient Report," near Petersburg, Va., 1865 Feb 15 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - 2nd Georgia Battalion, "Field Return," near Petersburg, Va., 1865 Feb 11 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - [33rd North Carolina Regiment], "Report of Guard mounted at the Fair Ground (Camp Branch)", 1862 Feb 15 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - [Anderson's Division], "Field Return," brigades of Wilcox, Mahone, Posey, Wright, and [Perry?], 1864 Jan 10
    - "Commutation of quarters" form, for S. J. Grant, Richmond (2 fragments), 1865 Apr (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "Commutation of rations," 2 forms, for privates Scott and Waller, 1864 Jul 27 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Contract of William A. Carrington, Acting Medical Director, with Private Physician A .G. Jones, 1863 Jan 17 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Discharge paper for Private [N.R.T?] Christopher, of Taylor's Regiment, 1863 Jan 14 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - General Hospital no. 9, Richmond, "Monthly Certificate of the Continuance of Disability", 1865 Mar 22 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      For Private J. W. Curtis of 62 Va. Infantry, Imboden's Brigade
    - Headquarters, Dept. of Tenn., "General Order No. 29, Ladies' address to the soldiers of Longstreet's Corps", 1864 Mar 29 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Headquarters, Department of Henrico, 2 passes to visit prisoners Johnson and Pearce at Libbey Prison, 1863-64 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "List of Ordnance left on Morris Island on the night of its evacuation", 1863 Sep 6 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Mahone's (Anderson's old) Division, "Tabular Return of Captures made During the Campaign of 1864", [1865]
    - Mahone's (Anderson's old) Division, "Tabular Return of Casualties sustained during the Campaign of 1864", [1865]
    - Military Hospital, Richmond, "Evening Roll Call", 1865 Mar 25 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Military Prisons, Richmond, "Morning Report of Prisoners," 3 reports, 1 dated June and 2 dated December, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Military Prisons, Richmond, receipt for 30 officers, prisoners of war received from Major T. P. Turner, 1864 Dec 11 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Office of the Exchange of Prisoners, Richmond, statement regarding exchange of [Lieutenant William Cooper?], 1863 Jun 23 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Office of the Provost Marshal General, pass issued to [B.?] Moore for travel from Little Rock to Texas, 1862 Nov (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Pay voucher no. 31, for B. F. Rickard, 1864 Apr 30 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Rodes, R. E., General, "Report of operations of his Brigade at Seven Pines," signed D. H. Hill, 1862 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - "Surgeon's Certificate of Exemption" for Andrew Crawford, conscript from Augusta Co., Virginia, 1864 Apr 18 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Terry, Major General, fragment of an order, [1865 Apr 22?] (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - CONGRESS
    - "An Act to ammend an act entitled An Act to provide revenue from commodities imported from foreign countries", 1861 May 21 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Committee on Flag and Seal, proposed designs for the Confederate Flag, 1862 Mar (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Artwork by L. Augusta Faust of New Hope, S.C., and J.H.H. of Charleston, S.C.; accompanied by ALS from L. Augusta Faust to Vice President Stephens
    - Petition to the Senate signed by government employees, regarding salaries and currency depreciation, 1863 Mar 31 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "Resolutions on the death of Mr. Yancey, by Mr. Clay", 1863 Dec 17 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Senate Journal, manuscript notes, 1862 Feb 22 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - DEPARTMENT OF STATE
    - Estimate of Appropriations for April to June, signed by Secretary of State R. M. T. Hunter, 1862 Feb 13 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      Accompanied by ALS from Hunter to C. G. Memminger
    - Estimate of Expenditures for July to December, signed by Wm. M. Monroe, Secretary of State ad interim, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Passport issued to T. William Pemberton, signed by Secretary of State J. P. Benjamin, 1863 Jul 31
  - NAVY
    - Register for the Sloop "Rapparada" of Charleston, S.C., 1862 Jun 21
  - MEDICAL PURVEYOR'S OFFICE
    - Form to accompany Invoice of Hospital Supplies, Atlanta, Ga., signed George S. Mackie, 1862 Oct 29 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - TREASURY DEPARTMENT
    - Auditor's report for adjustment to the account of F. W. Sims, proprietor of The Savannah Republican, 1864 Jun 24 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Estimate of Appropriation for the purchase of cotton and tobacco, report to the Committee on Finance, 1864 Feb 12 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      Accompanied by letter from A. Roane, Chief Clerk of Produce Loan, to C. G. Memminger
    - Non Taxable Certificate no. 6912 for one hundred dollars with six percent interest, 1864 Dec 16 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Petition to C. G. Memminger, Secretary of State, by clerks in the department for higher salaries due to inflation, [1863] (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - 4 receipts for Treasury Notes, 1863-65 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - 2 Registered Bonds at four per cent interest, issued to Mrs Gallagher and to John F. Buckhalter, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - 4 Tax receipts and 2 checks, 1862-64 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Tax records of Adam Fix, of Augusta County, Virginia, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Transfer Draft for two million dollars, to E. C. Elmore, Treasury, 1864 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - WAR DEPARTMENT
    - Adjutant and Inspector General's Office Special Order 129, suspending Habeas Corpus in Salisbury, N.C., 1862 Jun 5 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Adjutant and Inspector General's Office Special Order 206, suspending Habeas Corpus in Atlanta, 1862 Sep 3 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Promotion certificate for Captain Septimus T. Wall, Judge Advocate, Major General Jones' corps, 1862 Oct 19 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - 6 requests to the Secretary of the Treasury for payment of appropriations, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - INDIVIDUAL STATE GOVERNMENTS
    - Alabama
      - Wilcox County, form letter of agreement of service in the Alabama Militia, signed by Thomas Lee, 1862 Mar 5 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Louisiana
      - New Orleans City Bond no. 61, for one thousand dollars, 1862 Mar 30
    - Mississippi
      - State Legislature, Resolution No. 2, "in relation to the practicability of using negro men in the armies [...]", 1863 Nov 23 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - South Carolina
      - Estimate of the value of a slave furnished for service on the Coast, 1864 Dec 1 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Texas
      - County of Austin, Oath of Office for Justice of the Peace John [Osteshout?], 1862 Aug 18 (Box 2, Folder 81)
      - County of Bexar, sentence passed on Henry, a runaway slave, 1864 Sep 1 (Box 2, Folder 82)
      - County of Fayette, Certificate of Exemption from Military Duty for W. B. Moore, 1863 May 7 (Box 2, Folder 83)
      - Guadalupe County, tax receipt of J. P. Turner, 1865 May 26 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Virginia
      - Pocahonta County, minutes of a meeting held at Hillsboro, 1861 Jun 3 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - OTHER DOCUMENTS
    - Drinkard, W. R., statement regarding his application for the Office of Chief of the Bureau of War, 1861 Dec 13 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - [U. S. Army] Headquarters, Military Post of Raleigh, N.C., permission to carry a gun issued to P. F. Pescud, 1867 Dec 6 (Box 2, Folder 87)
- Other Material, 1863, n.d.; Series III; 0.02; (3 folders)
  - Empty envelopes and paper "taken from the Rebel Congress Hall after the evacuation of Richmond" (Box 2, Folder 88)
    Three of the envelopes are addressed: one to J. M. Baker, one to Mr. Orr, and one to P. N. Gilson from the Office of the Commissioner of Taxes; several of the unused envelopes are made of wallpaper
  - Package of white foolscap paper manufactured by Greenville Paper Mills, Greenville, S.C., [1863] (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - 2 canvas letter bags, one marked "CST," the other "U. S. Ship Marion, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 90)
- Oversize, 1.67; (8 folders)
  - [Anderson's Division] "Field Return" (Series II), 1864 Jan 10 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 91)
  - Mahone's (Anderson's Old) Division Tabular Return of Captures (Series II), [1865] (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 92)
  - Mahone's (Anderson's Old) Division Tabular Return of Casualties (Series II), [1865] (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 93)
  - Flag designs (Series II), 1862 Mar 22 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 94)
  - Design for an alternative Confederate Flag by Mrs. C. C. Clay (Series II), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 94a)
  - Passport of T. William Pemberton (Series II), 1863 Jul 31 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 95)
  - Registration of sloop "Rapparada" (Series II), 1862 Jun 21 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 96)
  - Tax record of Adam Fix (Series II), 1865 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 97)
  - New Orleans bond no. 61 (Series II), 1862 Mar 30 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 98)